[Music]
e
foror
researcher
for
[Music]
for for
Jurgen shukra uh can you please
introduce yourself or our listeners in
few uh sentences and tell us about your
research and your field of expertise so
I I started off as a nuclear physicist I
did my PhD it's now 50 years ago 40
years ago in 45 years ago in heidenberg
Germany uh studying some exotic
reactions between what happens when two
very heavy nuclear we used uranium uh
Collide at what we at the time thought
High energies but inside was very
moderate energies uh to study nuclear
shapes and nuclear
interactions uh and then after my PhD I
at that time the center of uh nuclear
good Nuclear Physics was in United
States so my idea was to go to
Massachusetts uh uh but my professor at
the time he had started to work at CERN
in Europe
some much higher energies and he said uh
why don't you come by and have a look
and I thought not really
interested but anyway I had some friends
and so I said okay I I'll come there for
a month or two mhm and then I was St
there mountains so at least exactly so I
got stuck not not by the signs not by
way at least but by the mountains and by
the wine f f a good wine and sweet has
mountains and Sun happens to be exactly
in the
middle and so then I decided okay maybe
not too bad uh let let's try it for a
year or two and so I went to CERN I
started looking at more higher energies
more what we physics also think the
higher the energies the more detailed
you look at the matter the more
fundamental it becomes and so I got my
interest got caught also by the very
International flare of the of the CERN
lab I mean this is a I don't know
whether I should speak about CERN or or
what I get there so okay so that that
was when how I came actually to S and
then I event I got stuck
there so this happened 40 years ago this
happened pretty much 40 years ago so
congratulations actually there are many
bir birthday this year son happens to
have its 70th birthday this year I'm
there
I I happen to have my family first so
I'm one year older
so but I spent 40 years at at s so doing
this might be a slightly implied
question but which particles were
unknown when you were starting now
unnown to me or Unown unconfirmed so Hib
would be one of them and dou sets were
not know actually this was the time when
quarx started to be taken
uh very serious and and turning up in
all T in all colors and types at CERN
also in different particles but not all
quirks were known yet so in the
80s I don't think the top the top quk
was certainly not known the bottom cork
was was known so one cork was still
missing uh and the w and z so the
carriers of fours uh and of course
part these are the fundamental parties
and in terms of
uh less fundamental
particles tons
SW we call them pons chons lambdas these
are then combin these are com like with
Lego Stones you take qus and you combine
them in different numbers and colors and
types and then you can can build many
many many patterns and many of them are
still unknown mhm but fundamental
particles were mainly those it was and
the gravit one if you like was not yet
observed M so explain why you ended up
in Europe instead of United States but
why particle physics instead of
something else for the exact same reason
they founded CERN uh right after the
second World War uh it was the final the
final convention was signed in 54 which
is why where we have now the 74th
birthday but it was started around 49 so
really very shortly after the second
world war with the explicit aim of uh
stopping the brain drain of scientists
to United States to give them an
alternative in
europeo uh and in order to make an
attractive alternative all of Europe had
to work together no single country could
put up something which would have been
compatible to the United States so the
original promotant of of Sur thought uh
for to re keep the European Talent here
but ALS also start again collaborating
on the level of States uh with
populations which 5 years earlier were
still shooting at each other so it was
always meant to be competitive for
Science and conductive to
peace so I ended up in so 30 years later
exactly for the reason because it was an
alternative which was attractive
compared to what was at the United
States so it still works today and it
today works better than any time there
are more Americans now working CERN in
high physics than in the United States
so it's huge success story huge success
story so you okay and that's success
story for you and sorry just a why
particle physics and that's when you
were starting this the obvious choice
Nuclear Physics so I I started of purely
Nuclear Physics then I went for two
years into really Pary physics meaning
uh there was an and accelerator at the
time uh which actually shut down the
week before I came so it was not working
anymore but it was still lock of data on
on storage so I could analyze it uh this
was called the ISR the intersecting
storage ring which was the very first
collider of um protons or not not
electrons but protons electron colliders
that existed before but that very so it
was a very important machine because
since then we have build many more
colliders they built them United States
they built them uh it's so the next one
the NHC is one of those uh but that was
the first machine and there I worked for
two years really in in high physics what
I liked was uh the so I said it was the
international environment but also the
stimulating intellectual environment
Nuclear Physics if you are three you're
a lot if you're five you're a prow and
starting more than seven in one
experiment becomes becomes
sociologically difficult there you
entered I entered an experiment with 100
people so way above anything uh but I
liked it because it's very stimulating
you always find people to talk to you
always find people which help you uh and
you're critically looked at and you PR
looked at uh once a week and not once a
month or once a year like a nuclear
physics where that just less people to
interact so that I like and then after
two years I actually combined the uh
nuclear physics and the high nature
physics and we were doing what is called
relativistic heavy iron physics is a
researcher or particular researcher are
you satisfied with the results that CERN
produced like hi bosum I okay that
that's a very very wide question so
there are two answers you you're never
satisfied in the sense that uh that's
all you wanted to do you there's always
more
uh and you're always satisfied because
it's rare that something really doesn't
teach you anything even if an experiment
doesn't work it teaches something only
if you break something that you so
negative results are also also important
so what and I satisfied to first of all
I didn't work on the Hicks so I worked
on something else on the heav which we
might might speak later about um but
you're still part of it because actually
the guys who look for Le they sit in the
next office and so you meet them on the
corridor and why they will not tell you
the the hottest Secrets they will tell
you uh already what they are doing and
how far they are and so you're really
part of her so even if you're not
working yourself on the Hicks you're
still very close to where where the
things happen and clearly the Hicks was
a was a was a huge success now the LC
was built find the hi and we had a
pretty good idea that we would find it
so it was not like uh switching on let's
see whether we find it or not because we
did a lot of precision measurements in
the previous
experiments and if you measure something
with very high Precision often you can
extrapolate so you can look forward uh
what that means for other things and
indeed the the measurements they did
with completely different
particles uh showed slight deviations
from what you would expect if there's no
hick particle
so you could say from our measurements
very likely that the hick and his mass
is between 100 and 200 in in the units
we're using actually 100 times or 200
times as heavy as a proton so that was
pretty clear that the we knew where to
look and what to look
for so in that sense it was not a huge
surprise it was anticipated that we find
it but it's still a huge Triumph because
the he particle is a very weird and the
very weird history at least for me which
is I'm not an expert to the hi
parting uh but the hi parting is a
theoretical invention
so uh some 60 year no not 60 years ago
yeah 60 years ago in the
60s uh we started to have what we would
call a unified picture of high energy
physics before you had one theory for
one phenomen another theory for second F
and the third theory for the thir there
were all good but they didn't know about
each other there were three completely
distinct theories which know and so
starting the fs people uh and do you
know that probably not probably soly
even better than I because you're atic
theoretical
physicist uh started to see
commonalities and a Common Language
between all the theories um and they it
it looked beautiful at least to them I'm
not a theorist of it moderately
beautiful for me it look really
daunting I'm not I'm not I don't like M
but for they they look beautiful and so
I believe them uh and it could deal with
all these things on a in a Common
Language it's like if you speak the same
language and suddenly instead of uh
having somebody speaking Slovak and you
have no idea what he says and somebody
else speaking English you have no idea
that everybody was speaking the same
language and and and so the only problem
was what the was telling was nonsense
nonsense in the sense he made
predictions which were manifestly as
strong as as it gets it was predicting
that all particles have exactly zero Mar
they have no M problem problem pars has
zero Marth it does what light does it
runs away at the speed of light you
can't stop at least in vacuum you can't
stop aaring without Ms you can't go it
in wrestle uh and that's obviously
pretty wrong I mean we all have just
were discussing weight whether we are
too heavy or up that we all know we have
a fairly substantial
MTH and so that's a problem for a theory
if it's beautiful but wrong uh you would
say okay let's get a better Theory but
it was so beautiful that uh some people
thought how can we save the theory and
you couldn't introduce a maass into the
theory because if you would do it it
would give even more
nonsense so what Mr Hicks in in his
desperation came up with is we Define ma
as not what we think it is but it's
something else we we we Outsource mask
like we Outsource
now work he outsourced Mars and he cre
he he he postulated there is a guy who
is responsible for Mars he he called him
Mi he he didn't called him Mi he called
it I don't know why he called him and it
has no other job and no other property
than generate Ms pretty pretty weird
idea in order to generate MTH for
everybody and everything it has to be
everywhere you see if if there's a
particle and this other guy is not
around he he has no M so he would TR
away the speed of light okay so this six
particle had to be it had no properties
other than generating Mass it had a mass
itself also but no no other things what
we know it had no charge no spin no no
no anything no
color uh but it m and it had to be
everywhere that's why some people call
it got particle it's everywhere and it's
ter but it's a terrible name yeah and I
actually don't know why who invented it
probably the publish of the book and not
the author but I don't know it sounds
like it it sounds like anyway so he he
he said there is this particle he didn't
know anything about else other than that
this this guy is responsible for MTH
by every every by by entally U bothering
anybody else with a M so it didn't it
doesn't bother the photon because it's
still has but every other particle is
sort of bothered by the hi particle and
this bothering turns up as a nuts well
so that's pretty crazy isn't it kind not
to me it looks crazy anyway uh if the if
this beautiful framework should work you
needed the hi particle and so they
people started looking for the hi
particle they didn't know where it
appears because there was no prediction
I
mean nothing could tell you how heavy it
is and so we had to measure it and it
was searched the eventally in the 60s in
all accelerators and all world but then
until we had this um detailed
measurements at lab which gave us an
idea where it could be uh nobody had an
idea where it comes so it was looked
everywhere before never found uh until
the LC so that I think that's a big deal
that's a big deal you make the most
crazy prediction you can make for good
reason and then you ask your exp to be
right your problem to find it and yeah
and they do it and they do so this was a
huge success but people expect it we are
always like always not satisfied
something more that's why I are we
satisfied no yeah so for example super
symmetry it was still like
being hoped for yes but probably not
within
reach so when I when I when I before the
LC started um put always a a laundry
list of open questions which we may have
a chance to answering the answering at
LC and top is all with the he because
there we actually we had let's say a
pretty good idea that if it exists there
are always ways out so it could have not
existed so it's not like we knew it
exists and we just went Fair fine they
always way out to to not to live without
a hi or something else but that was on
top but then there was a big list of uh
dark dark matter Dark Energy extra
Dimensions um met anti met Symmetry and
I don't know how far down it went but
there were so we we we we do know we
have a lot of open questions actually if
you measure it in the content of the
universe uh we know about 5% of the
stuff which is there 95% we don't know
in terms of knowledge is probably even
worse because we don't even know how
much we don't know yeah but at least we
know already a few things unnown exactly
so and so that so there I think many
people
were thinking we would find uh at least
the dark matter and again there was
actually a good reason for that because
we know how much how much dark metal
there
is and we know now how did it
go
uh
roughly at which point it might have
decoupled the universe which then would
Define how heavy it is and if you took
Reas numbers for every that then you had
a prediction it should be at a at a math
that would be accessible to the LHC but
that was much less of a clear prediction
but still it was a clear hint there if
if it has a certain interaction for
which I we reason and if it is all of
the Dark Matter then we should find it
at we have a good chance to find it let
see that we didn't
find uh we didn't find hidden Dimensions
either we didn't
find the reason for was there any real
hope for those like creating microscopic
black Hol or is it was this more just a
PR St let no let's go down the list the
hick was the most likely the D matter
was fairly likely I mean if I would have
put money on it before I would have
maybe thought the odsa 3 to one mhm okay
not bad the it was maybe uh I mean three
30% so not 3 to1 odds but the 30%
probability he was more like
80% uh dark matter these are just my
random numbers feel free to 30 which
means very likely
nobody that's let's say one in a
100% And then Metro anti Metro that the
the CP
violation yeah no
because that was even less even less
even less because we know it's not part
on model and so you would have to you
understand that model so that what was
the number for Super
symmetry uh
wise that that depends strongly on who
whom you asked so if you would have
asked John Ellis which was one of the
um that's real maybe know him he looks
like a theorist so that's big
beer but a really big beer white beir
like unlike me and unlike you um he
would have put it also in the tenth of
percent I think many other people were a
bit more skeptic but but super symmetry
have a very wide range of possible even
though already now we are also closing
that space a little bit so super I
didn't have a bet I didn't know what to
bet on so you said the the thing you
like about CERN is there are plenty of
people you can talk to about something
you just meet someone at cafeteria and
discuss something so what is the Hot
Topic now what are you working on And
discussing so I'm doing any so me or son
you you me you okay I'm doing something
very different but has nothing to do
with any of these extra Dimension extra
partic we're doing we are
studying one part of the stand up one
the strong interaction qcd so the
nuclear force so that's what's
responsible for nuclear energy on one
side
nuclear uh atomic bombs on on the bad
side uh but but also the working of
stars and and everything so nuclear
forth uh is really something which we
don't see every day but is very much at
the core of what but now now the nuclear
force is a very strong force that's why
nuclei uh are very stable objects that's
why you get a lot of energy when you
when you take them
apart uh but on the theory side that has
a big disadvantage you can it's very
difficult to
calculate the equations are perfectly
well known they fit not only on a
t-shirt they fit on a on a tie they're
much smaller than the equation much
smaller than the equation of of
Relativity M maybe interesting in terms
of
size but you can solve them at least not
not easy analytically because the force
is strong so you cannot use what what uh
everybody else uses otherwise something
called perturbation theory meaning you
make approximation so you forget about
the details you make sort of a back of
the envelope calculations that gives you
the bulk and then you go to the next
level and say okay the bulk I have now I
look at the first refinement and that
gives me if I had 90% before now I'm at
95% and if I really want to go to 99% I
make two more approximations that
doesn't work with the strong force uh if
you take you make your first
approximation you get one number if you
make the second approximation suddenly
it changes by 100% if you make the third
it goes even negative so we we have an
episode B about quarx and GL so people
are famili with the headaches this is
causing okay so so that's why it
actually does help to um to do
experiments uh and then uh compare that
to your
calculations and so what we are doing is
we are we are looking at um one part of
the strong interaction which uh happens
at very high
temperature
so we are I mean believing in a very
cold Universe uh at least compared to
the time time Big Bang but if you go
back in the history of universe it
becomes fortron and then there is a
phase when all the structure the
complexity of particles and nuclei
dissolved into what we call a qulu and
plasma a soup where you only have these
element we think Elementary particles
the BS as the metap particles and the
gluons with the force particles and
there's no structure in it so there are
no protons neutrons nuclear no nothing
because the energy is to why we melt and
that is really what is thought to be the
the ground state the the state of lowest
energy of qcd that is and it has some
specific properties so you don't have
complex
objects um and good that's maybe
technical also you have chyal symmetry
so math disappear somehow in this fi so
that that was a prediction and we wanted
to test that and as good experimentalist
what you do you try to create that
matter and then measure its properties
so in order to create that we have to
just take a piece of matter and heat it
to about 100,000 100,000 times the
temperature in the core of the Sun and
then only that okay that difficult
straight forward straight forward the
way we do it in practice is so we take a
lead nuclear the biggest nuclear we can
find that's lead there are a few more
heavy but lead is is nice and round and
stable and easy to get cheap and cheap
actually our our colleagues in the
United States use gold which is about
the same just to show
off actually in the quantities you need
it doesn't matter they're using their
resource budget to the
fullest so we we are good good citizens
we use
lead so we have a a beam of flat which
we accelerate in the LHC so one beam
goes clockwise the other beam anticlock
wise uh to the highest energy we can we
can still store in in the LHC and then
we Collide them and when when when two
of these Le nuclei hit then their
kinetic energy so their velocity is by
friction transferred into heat so you
heat them up and you heat them up so
much that everything melts essentially
so the the nuclear melt the protons and
neutrons melt uh the energy appears into
por Inu and the you have
literally 10,000 of quark and gluons so
decent amount of matter which is the P
plasma at least that that was the idea
and then of course nothing can keep it
there so then like anything hot in
vacuum it starts to expand and cool and
become normal meure again and that goes
into architecture and will measure it h
uh what about the future of CERN because
uh there were some politicians that CERN
was only for finding Hicks and after
that it's uh useless uh do you do you
share this sentiment or very
surprising
so that can have be there can be two
reasons why they say one is we have
answered all questions so we don't need
to do any research and then they would
be right or they don't like basic
research and then they would be
wrong uh have we answered all questions
by far not I told you yeah you told many
questions we thought maybe we can answer
some of them at the LC and we can't and
what uh bigger uh cirle uh collider
would help in this effort or so so now
so the question now question is how to
how to where to look what to look for
and how to do
it uh on a time scale
which which is not unreasonable so we
don't want to do it in 100 years or 200
years because nobody body would be
around to do it because if you nothing
do then could do other things so uh what
can we do and of course with an amount
of money which does not sort of bankrupt
even the United States not not speak of
Slovakia or or Switzerland now switzland
could probably afford even more but
probably so so so that are let's let's
say the the framework so we we know
there are many questions now most of
them not all but many of them say okay
we haven't found these particles at NC
there's a fairly good chance that we
find them once we build better
instruments and that means higher energy
uh and more capable
detectors so that would mean U uh
machines accelerators which go to higher
energy now there are different types of
machines with which you can do
that uh but the only one which current
is practicable practicable is a bigger
version of the NHC there are ideas of
using very different types of particles
like even muons muons are the you
think I think they will they will know
what it mean it has been mentioned once
okay it's like an electron just heavier
and it has a big disadvantage for
accelerators it actually it's unstable
so it decays so unlike electron protons
which you can keep in the bottle till
you need them and M once you created it
you have to use it very quickly because
it case within millions of a second oh
millions of a second okay micro so it's
very hard to work with it exactly it's
now that's where relativity comes to the
rescue uh because if you accelerate them
very quickly to very high energies then
they live longer at least in their own
rest friend and uh if you so for them
time is
uh differently okay their own internal
framework they're still after micr but
for us outside who don't go with them
they can
live I mean in theory forever if you get
them to school apply it but in practice
they can live minutes but you have to
get them up very quickly because uh if
you don't do then they are dead by and
still the so they are very difficult
candidates to live through uh there are
other ideas but none of them currently
you could say
that is something with even a time scale
of 30 or 50 years you could build
already machines the the only thing
would be a machine with higher energy
there's one other there are two other
ways one can do it one is precision
measurement so instead of going to uh
bigger machines and uh try to create the
particles directly so using all the
energy and create them you can look for
indirect Effects by measuring very prec
precisely uh processes which you can
calculate and if there's a small
difference between what you measure in
your calculation then you know there are
additional ingredients which you need in
your theory so Precision man that's how
we actually predicted the Hicks already
before even seeing it by measuring
certain processes with very high
precision and then we saw differences
and that required the hi to be that M so
that we can do again in principle so
that's another possibility and that's
what they're doing now at the LC already
even if we cannot create new particles
we are trying now to measure the he
particle and how it what it does with
very high Precision that could tell you
could tell us already what happens in
higher energy so that's a second
approach so either directly high energy
or indirectly by high so these are the
tools and now
you want to ask commissioner someone for
we need 20 billion EUR to build this to
start so you know this is the tool so
what is this tool searching for so the
the the answer I mean it would be the
what what we hadn't answered before it
would be essentially Dark Matter dark
enery maybe not that that's it seems to
be we'll leave that for Next Century we
leave that for something to do some
super symmetry if if still there are
viable theories icted or not superm is
is a bit like the hix particle uh the
story of the hix superm is a very
beautiful Theory it again makes a a
common framework not only for all the
different interractions but all it even
unites now uh matter and force which is
a beautiful concept so that's why some
people have a very strong conviction say
that must be right such a beautiful idea
cannot be not used
uh but again it makes prediction then if
you don't find it so let's see so super
symmetry uh still has a certain space we
can look but it becomes less and less
attractive
MH uh and then there is still the this
question of matter antimatter symmetry
I'm not sure whether we could address
that I think it's mainly dark matter
which would be now let on my list the
top one this what the next number one on
the list and super number two H uh so
from what you said so far it seems like
particle physicist need to be very
attentive to details because you can see
the discovery maybe even decades before
it's done just from small deviations can
artificial intelligence be helpful in
this regard like looking at large data
sets and seeing patterns that you'll be
missing otherwise so so at the current
level it's already being used actually
we using intelligence in in in lower
versions uh as what's called booster
decision free and and so so not not that
GPT not large language ones but Neal
Network some detector triggers or uh do
we Us in the triggering that I'm not
sure I think mainly people use them in
the past in the analysis of the data
because I mean as you know you have to
train them you have to supervise them
you not sure you trust them already at
the trigger level
maybe now I mean there has been big
progress that that had just been but at
the analysis level we are using machine
learning sort of a more General appro as
also mentioned this morning in the inter
conference machine learning we use
already quite some time and it's being
used more and more but not large Lang
large language model used to write our
papers so that's yeah but still is there
a chance like you will plug
all it's probably impossible plug in all
LHC data into a huge artificial
intelligent model and then it will say
something like oh have you noticed that
when those electrons are going get
exactly those angles then you would have
really General artifici then you would
have ai General artificial in then you
would be on the level of u a human
currently you still have to guide it and
say okay this is what you I want want
you to look for this is how it should
look like now you tell me whether you
find them or not so you have to EXA you
you have to train so you train them on
monteal or on simulated data uh then you
then you or or on subset of your own
data you tell him uh this is the signal
this is the background that's how it
looks typically that's how the other one
looks here and now you tell me how many
of this in that type you find over in
there so for that we use artificial
intelligence and we don't we don't tell
him how to do it that it does by itself
by the associative learning but we tell
him what to do if one day you just give
him the data and tell him wake me up
tomorrow morning with the discovery so I
can phone stop on then we are talking
about artifici intelligence so we have
to wait maybe six more years we have to
wait I I I was discussing here with the
with with the the people here at at at
aset
who are really are much more expert than
I do we are we qualitatively or
quantitatively different from General
artificial intelligence so is it just
sort of scaling it up more and then we
are there or do we really need more
Quantum Chums really something even
different so not not only gradually
better but really bigly better they tell
me we need quantitative steps so and
quantitive steps you cannot time if it
would be scaling you could say maybe we
wait a year year or two or
five uh if we need let's say another
breakthrough it can come tomorrow or in
100 years so that's data so I'm not an
expert in that but we may have to wait
till tomorrow or suddenly new paper
archive with a good idea and yeah well I
mean like the Breakthrough in 2010 when
they went from um from the the shallow
neural Nets with only a few layers to
the Deep neural Nets and that really
made uh that made all the difference
that made all the difference then the
rest was just applying it find some nice
algorithms smoothing them and getting
the data through but that was a break
show you came to Slovakia in very
interesting time because uh also there
are asset signs at Wars and even Nobel
Prize uh have you had time to look at
the Nobel Prize for physics I I I read
it on on the on the web
yeah and what do you say about uh how
did you say
that well it's not really physics but so
I think the the the uh the subject uh
these artifici is really definitely
worthy Nobel Prize that's Nobel Prize
caliber in particular also in the spirit
of noble noble was not so much concerned
with breakthroughs on the fundamental
thing he was actually much concerned
about practical things which influence
Humanity so many of the first Nobel
prizes were very weird stuff
yes uh but but so it artificial
intelligence clearly is a big deal and
it fits very well in the noble my my
theory is they said we want to give it
to uh the Nobel Prize now it's not
chemistry it's not medicine it's not
peace it's not literature what's left is
phys
that's fine with it sounds like that
fine with me because actually that I
read why they took and they found a
story which you can make sense of uh but
anyway it doesn't matter so but it's
well the purpose of Nobel prizes to
bring the attention of to science maybe
shouldn't be just spread it a little bit
yeah maybe I could no is no longer
around but if you would clearly one
would I would have few advises what to
add I think if was around he would add
more prices because it's very difficult
to for computer science for me and maybe
mathematics mathematics mathematics
would if you look at the list of field
medals and PR is just impossible to
explain anyway so so we leave with that
and that's why I think uh having some
freedom in defining they do it anyway uh
I think the noble was here this week we
Emmanuel
shabon uh she got no Bri
chemist she's not considering really I
think she also think is more like
medicine or physiology
biology you have to but that's fine
that's fine you should not be you have
to go shortly so maybe our last question
will be well you
are fulfilling one of the oldest dream
of humanity to understand the matter
around us and what is the world composed
of it we have figured out a lot still a
lot of open questions so what would be
your recommendation for our young
listeners what should be studying they
should be studying and then go to the
fields to yeah see when I when I had the
choice uh physix was really that was the
right choice that was clearly in the 60s
and' 70s there were big breaks of the
still the quantum Revolution was was
what
whether I would would I would my
children today um recommend to do
physics anyway they wouldn't listen
so well some of them are listening any I
didn't so I don't have any physicist in
the family the
four but uh then sometime ago by I found
B biology U I had a really and still is
a very very active field men thing uh
noros
science Consciousness brain that I think
is one of the um Frontier
Sciences uh that actually relates also
to uh computer science I mean
NE brain complexity that that I think
are uh physics still has a lot of
interesting not only High leure physics
but also solid state physics is very
wide uh but there are it's not the only
game in town so what what I would
recommend actually uh everybody should
find out what he is most insistent when
I started actually I was interested most
in chemistry when I was little so I
little lab and I was to experiment
because it smelled and stank and and
that turned that into physics so if
somebody's interested in archaeology he
should by all means do
archaeology uh or what if somebody likes
the nature around uh the thing to touch
then physics is the right place if you
like the brain how how does complexity
this very nice talk also today how how
how thought Consciousness might right
rise out of as an emerging phenomena out
of out of something very basic but
complex that is a very interesting
subject to look into a very hard
lra there are SCI of frur everywhere and
the best advice I can give you choose
the the the direction which you're
passionate about I think every time we
ask we get a version of this
and without passion I think that's right
you don't you don't become researcher if
you don't love what you're doing if you
want to earn your money that's I not a
good place to earn
money P lawyer for
example for example
yeah okay thank you very much for your
time and speaking with us it was uh
quite pleasure on our side and hopefully
we will speak in
future again uh do you have some
something to add or something to want to
say to our listeners no no final word
okay thank you very much and see you
next time okay thank you thank you
[Music]
YouTube volam barbar Mar for
pod
[Music]